So, for this video, I want
to demonstrate CodeWorld.
And at the same time, try out my setup
for videotaping some live programming.
And then this is meant here as a first glimpse
of functional programming in CodeWorld.
Okay, so what is CodeWorld?
CodeWorld is the website that you see here.
And it is powered by Haskell.
So basically, in this area here, we can write
small Haskell programs that use a certain
library of graphics primitives.
And what we then get if we run this program
is the described picture or animation.
And the Haskell examples in the first few
weeks will mainly be based on CodeWorld.
So in theory, you could do the first exercises on
this website without a local Haskell implementation,
but sooner or later, you should also
install a compiler, of course locally.
Okay, so what's important is that you really
use the link for CodeWorld Haskell that is
provided in the Moodle course.
There's also another version of CodeWorld,
which is meant for kids' programming, so it
doesn't feature the actual Haskell language.
Okay, now, the first example, it's actually
not so much about functional programming,
but mainly about expression-
and value-based programming.
Okay, so let's take a look.
What we have here is a small program text
describing a scene, which apparently consists
of a circle, of a certain radius.
And then we have a more complex expression,
which is built from several parts.
So, there seems to be a polygon, which has three
pairs of numbers; so, probably that's three points.
So, this would be a triangle, and it gets a color
"red" and the "translation" here is not meant
in the sense of translating a language,
but actually in the sense of movement.
Okay, so that's a small Haskell program. It
was really a small complete Haskell program
using that library.
And what we can do here is we can
click Run, and what will we get?
Well, we get a picture of a circle, and a
red triangle that is somewhat moved outside
the center. So, the circle somehow has a
midpoint here, at the origin of the coordinate
system, and the triangle apparently was
translated or moved three units to the right.
Okay.
That's why we have this picture here.
One immediate question that sometimes arises
with such an example, when I first show this,
is: Why is the triangle right here and not
somehow first at the origin of the coordinate
system and then moved? Because after all, we
say something like: This is a red triangle, and
then it is translated to somewhere else.
So, one might expect naively that first we have a
triangle here, and then it's moved to the right.
But that's not actually what happens.
And the reason is that this is not a sequence
of computational steps that are described here,
it's really just an expression.
So, a value that should be computed.
And in this case, the value that would be
computed is this picture of a circle and,
moved to the right, red triangle.
Okay, and we can even use this button here to
inspect this in more detail. What do we get
then, here? That's also useful for
your own examples later on, probably.
And basically, we get a tree view of the expression
that we have built. So, we can open this here.
And then, as you see, when I hover with
the mouse over parts of the tree, then on
the left, I see the expression.
So, for example, if I am here,
then I just see the circle.
Or if I go here, then I see
the colored red triangle.
And actually, I can also make this
visible in the actual picture.
So, if I click on the circle,
then I see just the circle.
If I click on the polygon, then I would indeed see the
polygon in black at the origin of the coordinate system.
If I click on the subtree, which is the colored
triangle, then I see the same triangle but
in red, and then if I click on the subexpression,
which has this "translated" call, then I get
the to-the-right-moved red triangle, corresponding
exactly to what is highlighted here in the program code.
So, that's how subexpressions correspond to
individual pictures that, on the top level,
are combined to form the overall scene.
Okay, and, of course, you learn more
possibilities to combine expressions.
Okay, so that's a first glimpse
of this program and this website.
So, what I want to do now is to make this
a bit more complicated, step by step.
And the idea, of course, is not that you
should now fully understand the program that
I am writing here. The idea is really just
to get an impression of what I'm doing and
how a Haskell program might
look like, okay, and all
the syntactic details that I am now simply
using will, of course, later be explained
and introduced in more detail.
Okay, so what could we do? I will cheat a bit,
I will actually copy material from another
buffer, where I have already
played around before.
So, for example, one thing we could do
is actually introduce a few more forms.
So, let me, for example, say, I also want to
see a solid rectangle with certain dimensions.
So, it will be a square because it
has these two equal values here.
And I color it green, and I introduce it in
the sequence as just another picture that
I want to combine.
Okay, what happens when I run this?
I get this picture.
So, we see, for example, if things overlap,
which is the case here, right, we have the
circle at the origin, and also this solid
rectangle, then the thing that I mentioned
first will actually take precedence.
So if I, for example, were to move this around here,
then the circle should disappear behind the rectangle.
Okay, maybe I want it the other way around and
maybe I also want to change the sizes a bit,
so that I don't get such overlaps.
So, let's say I make the circle much bigger.
And let me also move the triangle
to the perimeter of the new circle.
What do I get?
Well, a picture that looks like that.
Okay, so now we have different forms, we have colors,
we have translation for moving something around.
And what else could we do?
We could, for example, say another transformation
that makes sense on shapes is rotation.
So, let's say we want to have this triangle,
rotated up here, then there's also a
library function for that.
It's called "rotated".
I can say I want to rotate,
what do I want to rotate?
Well, I have to add some brackets here.
That's why this red mark has appeared.
So, I have to put the thing that
I want to rotate in brackets.
Then, there is still an error here.
Okay, I think I have fixed that
with my additional bracket.
Maybe I didn't.
Now I have, but there seems
to be another problem.
Why is that?
Well, that now is a type error, which
is maybe not immediately obvious to you.
But I know what the problem is.
Namely, I should also say by what
amount I want to rotate my triangle.
And that would be an angle, of course. And in
CodeWorld, as in Haskell, angles are given in radians.
So, I have to say, half pi, for
example, if I want to have 90 degrees.
Let's do this.
And the error has disappeared.
Okay, so there's hope that if I now
compile this, I will get something useful.
Okay, so now I have my triangle up
here because it has been rotated.
Yeah.
Now, this is all very static.
So, I mentioned earlier that we
might also want to do animations.
So, what does it mean to be an animation?
Well, an animation depends on time.
What could this mean here?
And we don't simply have a drawing,
we need to have an animation.
Okay, that's something that I know
by heart, I need this other function.
Then there is, again, a type error.
Why is that?
Well, what does it say here?
I have something of the type Picture.
But to be an animation, I would actually have
to have something of type Double to Picture.
Why is that?
Because "animation", essentially, is
a function from "time" to Picture.
Okay, and I can make this happen by
introducing a parameter in this scene here.
I can say, well, there's some time parameter,
t.
Then I can run this again.
It will work, but do nothing
else than it did before.
Why is that?
Basically, because I haven't
used the time parameter, t.
How could I use it?
Well, if I want this triangle to move around,
maybe I should make the angle by which
I rotate the triangle dependent on the time.
So, instead of having pi/2, I could say
something like t, which is measured in seconds,
by half of pi.
It would mean that after one second, I would be
where I am right now, here in this previous example.
And as t increases, this will change.
Okay, let me run this again.
Okay, this is moving quite quickly.
So, if I want to change this, I could, of
course, simply change some parameters here,
I could, for example, say it should only
rotate in one second by a quarter of pi,
so by 45 degrees.
And if I do this again, then
I will get a slower animation.
Okay, so that's something I can do.
Now there's a delay, probably because my video capture
interferes with the computation of the Pictures.
Okay, so that's still a bit boring.
What else could I do?
Let me cheat a bit again by copying something,
and then explaining only very
briefly what's happening.
Let me add this, and let me actually turn
the triangle back into a static triangle,
so, not moving around, why?
Because I will, anyway, be
using the t parameter down here.
So, I will still have something dynamic.
Okay, let me first remove this "rotated"
call, simply by out-commenting it.
And then I will first explain what this means.
And then we can think about the rotation.
Okay, what do we get if it were this?
Okay, so that's something interesting.
What happened here?
Well, apparently, I have now drawn many squares
or rectangles, right? I did something similar
to the solidRectangle up here,
but I omitted the "solid".
So, I just draw a rectangle.
And then the parameters here are not simply
4 and 4, but something bigger, 4 + a.
Where does the "a" come from?
Well, I simply expressed that "a" comes from a
certain set or a certain list, namely the list
[0, 0.5, ... 9] up to nine. The meaning being that
actually, by this highlighted expression here,
"a" will be chosen from each of 0, 0.5,
1, 1.5, 2, etc., up to 8.5 and 9, so
something like 18, 19 or 20 values for "a", and for
each value of such an "a", this rectangle will be drawn.
So, in some sense, that's similar to a loop
or a "for" expression (for-loop) in languages
like C or Python.
Okay, but it's not really a loop in the real
sense, because it's not about doing one step
after another, but actually about saying I want
to have that many rectangles, and they vary
according to this parameter.
So, it's actually more like a set expression
that you use in mathematics: the set of all such
and such so that a certain condition holds.
Okay.
So, in that sense, in this way, I
get this more complicated picture.
And then if I want to make this even more fancy,
I can say well, let me also rotate these squares.
Yes, I could add something like "rotate" it,
and again, something dependent on t as before.
Say, let me rotate each picture by
something like this, for example.
Then, they would all rotate at
the same speed around the origin.
Okay, and then actually, the expression that
I had here before was a bit fancier even,
because it computed the angle by
which each individual square has to be
rotated from both a and t.
So, not the same angle is actually used for
all the squares, but actually also the "a"
value is integrated, and it may not be easy
to imagine what this will look like, but you
can simply try it out and see what happens.
Okay, that may not be the most useful program,
such an animation, but at least it gives you
a first impression of both this website and
the way we will be using it to describe
pictures and animations, etc.
And by doing so, we get to
know the constructs of Haskell.
Okay.